<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Brent Limyansky, PhD</title>
    <description>A website to showcase my personal projects.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2023 16:46:59 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2023 16:46:59 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a Website: A Physicist's Perspective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A common piece of advice for those transitioning from academia to industry is to build a personal portfolio of projects to show off your skills and talents.
One of the first elements to building such a portfolio is deciding how to display it.
In creating my own website, I sought something cheap and easy to write, but also over which I had a large degree of creative control.
I also thought it would be fun if I could use my own domain name.
These requirements pushed me towards &lt;a href=&quot;https://domains.google.com&quot;&gt;Google Domains&lt;/a&gt; to manage my domain name, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; to host my website, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;jekyll&lt;/a&gt; for formatting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I will discuss how I came to this final setup, as well as various prior attempts at website generation.
I consider this “A Physicist’s Perspective” because my ultimate decision makes use of skills I’ve acquired during my time in academia, specifically GitHub, Linux (optional, but command line is a must), and Markdown, as well as an existing Google account.
I have opted not to make this post a specific tutorial, and will mostly focus on providing an overview of my setup.
If you are interested in a tutorial, I recommend looking at GitHubs &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/pages&quot;&gt;official documentation&lt;/a&gt;.
This will walk you through everything I discuss below, including using jekyll to build web content and write blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-and-hosting-a-website&quot;&gt;Building and Hosting a Website&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For amateur setups, the choice of tools used to build and host your website are intimately intertwined.
Some hosting providers will require you to use a specific piece software to build your website, while others have certain technical requirements that won’t work with particular development software.
If you have a strong preference in regards to software or web host, I recommend starting there and finding a complimentary service that will work well your choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hosting&quot;&gt;Hosting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew almost immediately that I wanted to host my website on GitHub Pages.
This is a free service provided by GitHub that will host any of your public repositories as websites.
It even gives you the option of connecting a domain name that you already own!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For someone already familiar with GitHub, selecting a repository branch to be served as a website involves changing only a single setting.
Managing the website is done through exactly the same procedures as managing any other repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in my personal experience, GitHub has a steep enough learning curve that getting it set up exclusively to host a website may not be the best option for everyone.
My limited experience with &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.com&quot;&gt;WordPress.com&lt;/a&gt; showed it to be a more user-friendly experience, although this comes at the cost of, well, money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building&quot;&gt;Building&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub Pages limits you to hosting &lt;em&gt;static&lt;/em&gt; websites.
These are websites that provide identical content for all users, such as what one typically expects of a personal blog.
Static websites are contrasted with &lt;em&gt;dynamic&lt;/em&gt; websites, where content is generated via an app on a user-by-user basis.
Most online retailers will use dynamic websites, which build their webpages by querying databases for the products most likely to appeal to each specific user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WordPress software suite, although free and open source, natively generates dynamic websites that won’t work with GitHub Pages.
There are some workarounds, such as the SimplyStatic plugin, but I had trouble getting these tools to work properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also considered the bare-bones option of writing the website in raw HTML and CSS.
I found this to be the simplest path forward, as it doesn’t involve tinkering with any software other than a text editor.
However, your website will inevitably end up looking like it is from the 90’s.
My HTML/CSS attempt is still alive at &lt;a href=&quot;https://limyansky.github.io/&quot;&gt;limyansky.github.io&lt;/a&gt; (hey, its free!), for all those interested in taking a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this trial and error, I settled on using jekyll to build my website.
This software is built with Ruby, and easily translates &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markdownguide.org/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; documents into decently looking websites.
Like any good tool, the sky’s the limit!
For examples of what the pros can build jekyll, take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.spotify.com/&quot;&gt;Spotify for Developers&lt;/a&gt; and the website for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foia.gov/&quot;&gt;Freedom of Information Act&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my purposes, I’m already familiar with Markdown via my use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsidian.md/&quot;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt; as a note taking app in academia, which makes writing new blog posts a breeze.
Jekyll is also explicitly mentioned by GitHub as working well with Pages, with the GitHub team going as far as including specific tutorials for certain aspects of its use.
Although I have no prior experience with Ruby, which did cause some confusion during setup, jekyll is popular enough that tutorials and StackExchange questions are plentiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-note-on-domain-names&quot;&gt;A Note on Domain Names&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Registering a domain name is a comparatively simple process - you find a domain registrar (Google Domains and NameCheap are popular examples) and pay them a few dollars to claim your desired name.
There may be a few settings to tweak when connecting your domain name to your hosting service, but tutorials are abundant from registrars and hosting providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, something very important to keep in mind is that missing a payment (although most services offer a grace period) on your domain name means you are likely to lose access to the name for a number of years.
Rather than simply being de-listed, old domain names are often auctioned to investors looking either to resell them for a profit or make money from their existing user base. 
One organization I was previously involved with lost their domain in this manner, although it was eventually de-listed about two years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this is to say that I chose Google Domains not only because I found their pricing competitive ($12 at the time of writing), but because I knew I could keep up to date with the payments if I associated them with my existing google account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the most challenging part of making this website to be selecting software and providers that would work well together.
I hope that by going into detail on what I finally settled on, I can save you some time in designing your own website.
Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/Building-A-Website/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Building-A-Website/</guid>
        
        
        <category>project</category>
        
        <category>github</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
